Finding Aid for the John R.G. Gosling Papers 1897-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John R.G. Gosling Papers 1897-1984 1950-1975
Gosling, John R.G., 1926-1992
9776 Aa 2
Professor of obstetrics and gynecology and associate dean of the Medical School, 1964-1981; papers include files on the history of the University of Michigan Medical School, teaching and research files, some medical school administrative records and personal and professional correspondence.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Enid Gosling (Donor No. 8545 ) in 1996 and 1997.
The collection is open for research.
John R.G. Gosling was born in Cleveland, Ohio, in 1926. He entered the University of Michigan as an undergraduate in 1944. He then attended the University of Michigan Medical School, receiving his degree in 1950. After a stint in the military, Gosling returned to the University of Michigan as an instructor, first in pathology and then in obstetrics and gynecology. He joined the full time faculty of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology in 1957 and became an associate professor in 1962. In 1964, he was appointed an assistant dean of the Medical School. In 1968, he was appointed to an additional position, assistant professor of Postgraduate Medicine. He retired from the Medical School in 1986. During his career at the university, he published many research articles and a textbook, Fundamentals of Gynecology. He also studied and lectured on the history of medicine. In 1991, the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology established a lectureship in Dr. Gosling's name.
The Gosling collection, covering the years from 1897 to 1985, has been divided into three series:
Medical Research
Historical Research
Personal/Administrative Files.
The Gosling collection consists of research files on obstetrical and gynecological issues, historical files on the University of Michigan Medical School, lecture notes, and student medical notes ca. 1897-1900 (author unknown).
Subjects:
Gosling, John R. G.; Obstetrics.; Gynecology.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Obstetrics and Gynecology.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Miller, Norman Fritz, 1894-
- Medical Research 1950-1975
  The Medical Research series consists of notes, correspondence, manuscripts, and secondary material concerning contemporary medical topics, generally in the field of obstetrics and gynecology. The files are arranged alphabetically. Most of these files date from the period from 1950 to 1975.
  - Abortion (Box 1)
  - Adenocarcinoma of Cervix, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Amenorrhea, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Journal of Surgery Article 1963 (Box 1)
  - Benign Uterine Tumors (Box 1)
  - Bowen's Disease of the Vulva, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Cancer: Experimental (Box 1)
  - Cancer: Immunology (Box 1)
  - Carcinoma Cervix, Pregnancy, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cervix Carcinoma (Box 1)
  - Cervix Cancer, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Carcinoma of the Vulva, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Case Histories 1966 (Box 1)
  - Coagulation Disorders in Pregnancy: Manuscript 1963 (Box 1)
  - Contraceptive Study (Box 1)
  - Controlled Labor: Sandoz Research 1963 (Box 1)
  - Diabetes in Pregnancy (Box 1)
  - Dystocia (Box 1)
  - Dysmenorrea 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Endocrinology (Box 1)
  - Endometrial Biopsy (Box 1)
  - Extracorporeal Circulation of the Human Placenta 1961 (Box 1)
  - Heart Disease and Pregnancy (Box 1)
  - Induction of Labor (Box 1)
  - The Infant (Box 1)
  - Infiltrative Squamous Cell Carcinoma of Vulva 1961-1962, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Intern Stipends in Teaching Hospitals 1959-1961, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Intrauterine Device Study 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - In Vitro Fertilization 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Medical and Surgical Complications (Box 1)
  - Medical Television 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Medico-Legal Gynecology (Box 1)
  - Nausea and Vomiting in Pregnancy 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - Office Diagnosis of Gynecologic Cancer 1961 (Box 1)
  - Oral Contraceptives (Box 1)
  - Ovarian Tumors: Texarkana Conference 1963 (Box 1)
  - Pathology Seminar Material 1968-1975 (Box 1)
  - Pelvic Sarcomas (Box 1)
  - The Pelvis (Box 1)
  - Perinatal Surveys 1962-1963, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Postpartum Hemorrhage (Box 2)
  - Pregnancy 1961 (Box 2)
  - Prematurity (Box 2)
  - Prolonged Labor (Box 2)
  - Prolonged Pregnancy (Box 2)
  - Psychosomatic Gynecology (Box 2)
  - Radiation Physics (Box 2)
  - Research: Miscellaneous Proposals (Box 2)
  - Physical Diagnosis: Judge-Zuidema (Box 2)
  - Third Trimester Bleeding 1960 (Box 2)
  - Trophoblast Mitosis Studies 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Vaginal Agenesis 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Vaginal Carcinoma 1953-1961 (Box 2)
  - Vulvar Disease; American College of Surgeons Panel 1964 (Box 2)
- Historical Research
  The Historical Research series consists of notes, manuscripts, secondary material and some primary material collected by Gosling. The series includes a group of late 19th century lecture notes from the University of Michigan Medical School.
  - Norman Miller Papers 1938 (Box 2)
  - Medical School: Historical Materials 1924 (Box 2)
  - History of the University of Michigan Medical School 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Gosling's histology, embryology, and bacteriology notebooks 1947 (Box 2)
    (from the Historical Center for the Health Sciences collection)
  - Gosling's Surgery Notes 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified University of Michigan Medical Lecture Notes 1897-1900, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - History of Medicine; miscellaneous material 1940-1960 (Box 2)
  - History of Medicine Lecture Notes (Box 2)
  - History of Medicine; miscellaneous material (Box 2)
  - William Beaumont 1943-1967 (Box 2)
  - James Graham (Box 2)
  - History of Prostitution (Box 2)
- Personal/Administrative Files
  The Personal/Administrative Files concern the administration of the Medical School and Gosling's private practice. Also included in this series is material relating to the Gosling residence known as "Brushwood" in Barton Hills. The residence was designed by Emil Lorch and was built for Alex Dow, president of the Detroit Edison Company around 1923. Records include architectural drawings, photographs of the interior, and miscellaneous material relating to the history of the house and Barton Hills.
  - "Brushwood" (Barton Hills Residence)
    - Architectural Drawings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous 1923-1991 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1930 Photographs (Box 2)
  - Malpractice Suit 1976 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Student Research 1963 (Box 2)
  - Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge, (CRUSK) 1966 (Box 2)
  - CRUSK Correspondence 1964-1970 (Box 2)
  - Dean's Seminar 1970 (Box 2)
  - Inter-Mountain Regional Medical Program 1969 (Box 2)
  - Professional Correspondence 1984 (Box 2)